<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to a member of Parliament, occasion'd by the votes of the House of Commons against their late Speaker, and others</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48193</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12892312</idno>
  <idno type="VID">95142</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240855653</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1678</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3846</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12892312</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48193)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95142)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 718:42)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to a member of Parliament, occasion'd by the votes of the House of Commons against their late Speaker, and others</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On the conviction of Sir John Trevor and others for accepting bribes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Trevor, John, --  Sir, 1637-1717.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Commons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Political corruption --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95142:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER TO A MEMBER of PARLIAMENT, Occasion'd by the VOTES OF THE <hi>House of Commons</hi> Against their Late SPEAKER, and Others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:95142:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95142:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER TO A MEMBER of PARLIAMENT, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Inquiry</hi> your Honourable <hi>House</hi> has made of late into the <hi>Corruption</hi> of some of its <hi>Members,</hi> and the Marks of Infamy you have put upon them, does give a general Satisfaction here in the Country. The hopes which your late <hi>Votes</hi> have rais'd in all Good men, to see at last a stop put to the crying Oppression of some in Places of Trust and Profit, do in some little measure make amends for the dismal Prospect the Death of <hi>our Incomparable Queen</hi> had occasion'd. If once the <hi>Bloodsuckers of the Nation</hi> be search'd for, in order to condign Punishment, there is nothing in their Power that the People of <hi>England</hi> will not chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95142:3"/>do to support His Majesties Government, and carry on the present War: And it's chiefly from their <hi>Representatives</hi> in Parliament that they expect such a Search and Inquiry.</p>
            <p>You have already vindicated the Honour of your <hi>Illustrious Body,</hi> in sending one of your <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> to the <hi>Tower for taking a Bribe,</hi> and in finding <hi>another</hi> of them, for taking a Gratuity, <hi>guilty of a high Crime and Misdemeanour,</hi> and then afterwards <hi>expelling</hi> him for so doing. By these <hi>Votes</hi> you have confert'd an Immortality upon two Gentlemen, that might have been otherwise lost in History. And while the <hi>Archives</hi> of this Parliament continue in being, their Names will be perpetuated to after-Ages.</p>
            <p>It's true, it will look but with an ill Grace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, to hear of one of the <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>English</hi> Parliament sent to the <hi>Tower</hi> for <hi>Bribery:</hi> So great a Name for the most incorrupted Body of Men in all <hi>Christendom</hi> has the House of Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ever born. But when they come to know what a Post this Man was in, and what yearly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes belong'd honestly to his Place, even more than what some that take Rank among Princes are possess'd of in other Countries; Nothing but the highest Resentments of that Honourable House against him can attone for the Reproach he has
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95142:3"/>brought upon the Nation by so mean, and dirty a Crime.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ne vel Marcus</hi> became a Proverb among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> in the Declension of that Empire; intimating, that the Corruptions, the Vices, and Divisions of the subsequent Ages were come to that height, that even the Reign of a <hi>Marcus Antoninus</hi> would not be capable to reform or restore <hi>debauch'd and sinking Rome.</hi> That Excellent Person, who gave rise to the Proverb, was reputed the best of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers, the best of Princes, and the best of Men. By his admirable Conduct and Example, he put a stop for a while both to the Vices of the Age, and to the Inundation of Misery that then threatn'd, and afterwards overwhelm'd the <hi>Roman</hi> State. Yet all his Vertue, and all his skill in the Arts of War and Politicks, could do no more but prop up, during his own time, a shatter'd Fabrick, and a tottering Empire. <hi>Rome</hi> was rotten at the heart, and there was not Virtue enough left to carry through the <hi>Glorious Reformation,</hi> and noble Designs which had been so happily begun by <hi>Antoninus.</hi> The preceding Reigns had utterly deprav'd the <hi>Roman</hi> Genius. And so far were they from imitating those Actions of their Ancestors that had fill'd three Parts of the Globe with their Fame, that they were then become willing to forget quite that they had been once Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the World.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95142:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Antoninus</hi> did all that Man could do, both in the Arts of Peace and War. He not only deliver'd <hi>Rome</hi> from foreign <hi>Invasions</hi> that threatn'd the very Center of the Empire; but carri'd his Arms in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son beyond its usual <hi>Boundaries,</hi> both on the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West,</hi> and brought under his Dominion seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Nations that had never before submitted their Necks to the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoke. At home he restor'd the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate (or <hi>Parliament</hi>) to its <hi>Ancient Rights,</hi> which had been invaded by some of his Predecessors: And by his own Example did all that was possible to bring Virtue into request. But alas! All his Efforts were in vain. <hi>Rome</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Sink of Vice and Corruption; and even <hi>Antoninus</hi> was not sufficient to Reform the Age! Yet Heaven was pleas'd by his Means, and for a Reward to his Virtue, to put a stop for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable time to the Fate of his Country: But not long after he was gone, the Divine Vengeance refus'd to be atton'd, and that proud City that had given Law to Mankind for a great many Ages, fell at last a Prey to Barbarous Nations, whose Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Language, and Customs they did not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, and some of whose Names they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of.</p>
            <p>I pray God, Sir, there may be no ground for a Parallel betwixt <hi>Rome</hi> at that time, and <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95142:4"/>now. I would fain hope that it may be in the Power of a Prince that possesses all the good Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Antoninus,</hi> to retrieve <hi>England</hi> from the Fate it deserves. And yet you'll agree with me, That in most kinds of Vice we exceed <hi>Rome</hi> it self, even in its most degenerated Times.</p>
            <p>I confess there are some Vices, that instead of bringing Ruin to a Countrey, may help sometimes, <hi>by Accident,</hi> to raise it to a higher Pitch of Glory. Such are <hi>Ambition, Emulation,</hi> and <hi>Thirst after Dominion.</hi> These were the <hi>Darling Vices</hi> of the Ancient <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and the <hi>Illustrious Crimes</hi> by which, from a Beggarly Village, they rose to the Universal Monarchy. There are others that natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tend to the Destruction of a State, such as <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousness, Corruption, and preferring Private Interests to that of the Publick.</hi> These last were seldom or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of in the first and best Ages of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire. The Genius of <hi>Rome</hi> mov'd in a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Orb: <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Renown</hi> were the Deities they ador'd; nor could the <hi>Roman Eagle</hi> stoop to so low a Quarry as that of <hi>Gold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Time was, <hi>My Friend,</hi> when <hi>Cincinnatus</hi> was brought from the Plow, to take upon him the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Command;</hi> and when he had sav'd his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, he return'd to his Plow again. His whole
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95142:5"/>Estate, when he came to be <hi>Dictator,</hi> was but <hi>Seven Acres of Ground;</hi> and so far was he from purchasing more, that he sold Three of them to pay what he had fallen short of in his <hi>Publick Accounts.</hi> There was a time, when a <hi>Paulus Emilius</hi> in his Triumph over <hi>Perseus,</hi> carried up with him to the <hi>Capitol</hi> the Inestimable Spoils of the Kingdom of <hi>Macedon,</hi> which the Kings of that Countrey had been heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up for some Hundreds of Years. Of all that vast Amass of Treasure the Noble Conqueror kept nothing to himself; and when he came to dye, all he left behind him was not sufficient to make a tolerable Maintenance for his Wife. <hi>A Glorious Poverty, and a Renown'd Want!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Inimitable Patern of Magnanimity and Love to his Countrey, <hi>Attilus Regulus,</hi> after he had destroy'd the Riches of <hi>Carthage</hi> by the Success of many Battels, being in <hi>Africk</hi> he came to understand that the Senate had continued his Command for a Year longer: Whereupon he writes a very earnest and submissive Letter to the <hi>Consuls,</hi> telling them, <hi>That the Bailiff of his little Farm in the Countrey was dead, and that one he had hir'd since, was run away with the Utensils of his Husbandry; and therefore desires Leave to come home, lest his Land lying untill'd, his Wife and Children should want Bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:95142:5"/>
            <p>What need I to instance more of this kind? The <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Story are full of them. But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you may say, These men had no opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be Rich, and therefore it was against their will they dy'd so Poor. No, Sir, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, all these I have nam'd wanted no opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to enrich themselves if they had pleas'd: Not only vast Sums of the Publick Money past through their hands, but immense Riches of Conquer'd Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces. These Men fought for their <hi>Countrey,</hi> for <hi>Liberty,</hi> for <hi>Glory,</hi> and scorn'd to stoop to any other Recompence, but <hi>the Praise and Satisfaction of their having done well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But perhaps you may yet tell me, They were Fools in all this. Be it so, as the world goes now: But let me tell you, It was by such <hi>Follies</hi> as these, that <hi>Rome</hi> not only conquer'd Countries, but Hearts too; and together with their Arms did propagate <hi>Morality, Civility, Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences,</hi> among the Numberless People they subdued.</p>
            <p>If you ask me, How came it to pass then, that notwithstanding all these Sublime Virtues of the Ancient <hi>Romans, Rome</hi> became at length a Prey, first to its Fellow-Citizens, and afterwards to Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Nations? I answer, It was <hi>Corruption</hi> that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion'd this Wonderful and Dismal Change. When Virtue and Merit entitled Men to Employments in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95142:6"/>the Commonwealth, <hi>Rome</hi> was Great and Happy; but after that Money came into the Scale, such men came into Places as became both <hi>the Bane and the Shame of the</hi> Roman <hi>State.</hi> What was it that brought the <hi>Grecian</hi> Governments, so much celebrated in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient History, to ruin? Was it not <hi>Corruption? Philip of Macedon</hi> made his Advantage of it: He Bought more Cities than he Conquer'd; and bragg'd that there was none so strong, but an Ass laden with Gold might enter into it. What was it that made <hi>Carthage,</hi> the once <hi>Rival of Rome,</hi> to become a <hi>Heap of Rubbish?</hi> Was it not <hi>Corruption?</hi> The Brave <hi>Hannibal</hi> found it a harder Task to struggle with the <hi>Corrupted Faction</hi> of <hi>Hanno</hi> at Home, than to wage War against the <hi>Romans</hi> Abroad; and the once flourishing <hi>Carthagenian Commonwealth</hi> became first a Prey to the Avarice of its own Citizens, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore she was forc'd to submit her self to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering Sword of <hi>Scipio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, Sir, give me leave to do both the <hi>Romans, Greeks,</hi> and <hi>Carthagenians,</hi> the Justice, as to acquit them of one kind of <hi>Corruption</hi> that's to be found in the Age we now live in; I cannot call to mind, that ever they enrich'd themselves with the Money that was destin'd for the Safety of their Countrey; nor can you give any Instance of one of them that fill'd his own Coffers with what was given by the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95142:6"/>People <hi>for Maintenance of their Armies in Times of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent hazard of their State.</hi> Even in the most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated Ages of the World, it was accounted <hi>Sacriledge</hi> to divert to any private use the Money that was set apart for <hi>so great an End.</hi> Among all Nations, such Money was held equally Sacred with that appointed for the Service of their Gods; and to purloin the least <hi>Farthing</hi> from either the one or the other was ever branded with the blackest mark of Infamy.</p>
            <p>If ever there was a time when a Crime of this Nature admitted of the highest Aggravations, <hi>now</hi> is the time. It's <hi>now,</hi> that <hi>England</hi> has its <hi>All</hi> at Stake, and upon the Success of this War depends not only its <hi>own,</hi> but the <hi>Fate</hi> of <hi>Christendom.</hi> We fight not now for Glory, Dominion, or a point of Honour, but for <hi>Liberty,</hi> for <hi>Religion,</hi> for our <hi>Laws,</hi> our <hi>Properties,</hi> and in a word, for <hi>all we can wish for to make us Easy and Happy.</hi> Our <hi>Fleets</hi> and <hi>Armies</hi> carry with them the Fortunes of Three Kingdoms, and the meanest Soldier and Seaman in the King's Service has intrusted to him some share of <hi>this mighty Stock.</hi> The Money rais'd at this time by Act of Parliament, is the Money of the Nation. Every one bears a share in it, and every one expects too, that it should be appli'd for the Publick Safety, since it's so nobly given for defraying <hi>the Charge of the most
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95142:7"/>necessary, and the most important War this Nation was ever hitherto engag'd in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's for such a War as this, that all Nations, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Pagan</hi> or <hi>Christian</hi> have thought it no Sin to make use of the <hi>Utensels of their Churches and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and of the <hi>Sacred Treasures</hi> they or their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors had dedicated to the Service of the gods they ador'd. Must it not then be a Sacriledge of the deepest die, to rob these our Armies or Fleets of any part (tho never so small) of the Money appointed for them; when to borrow from the <hi>Altar</hi> to pay them, would be none? It's true, and thanks to Heaven for it, we are under no such hardship at present, and there is ground enough to hope we may bring this War to a happy period, without being put to any such necessitous Shifts to defray the Charge of it. But still these <hi>Blood-suckers</hi> of the Nation that defraud our Soldiers or Seamen of never so little of their Due, are as guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as if we were actualy reduc'd to such an Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity as I have now mention'd.</p>
            <p>Shall they every day for our Sakes expose their Lives to a thousand dangers, and look Death in the Face in a thousand various Shapes, while in the mean time we enjoy a perfect Ease and Quiet at Home? And yet shall there be found amongst us, any one that at one single <hi>Bribe</hi> dare filch as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95142:7"/>much of their Money, as <hi>would maintain at full Pay near three hundred Soldiers for a Month?</hi> In which case it's hard for a Man that loves his Country, not to wish an <hi>Anathema</hi> to the <hi>Giver,</hi> and much more one to the <hi>Receiver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Neighbours here in the Country plague me with a thousand Questions about Mr. <hi>G</hi>—. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they ask me, What great things this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath done for his Country, that he deserves so profitable a place? They expect I should ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint them with some signal Opposition he had made to the violent Courses of the last Reigns, or of some great Losses he sustain'd by them: They will needs be inquiring about his Behaviour, with relation to the <hi>late Revolution,</hi> and what wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Atchievements he has done for the support of the present Government? But, I, not having the honour to be known to the Gentleman, am not able to answer to all these Questions, and therefore I must intreat you, who possibly know him, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve them for me.</p>
            <p>Tho this be no laughing matter, yet I cannot omit to tell you a pretty ridiculous Passage that fell out here t'other day. Mr. <hi>G.</hi> and Sir <hi>J. T.</hi> being the Subject of the Discourse, as they seldom fail to be of late, an honest Neighbour of mine, but none of the greatest Politicians, you may easily guess, would needs out of pure good Nature extenuate
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95142:8"/>Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s fault, by saying, That perhaps he had a numerous Family, and might be tempted to take 200 <hi>Guineas</hi> to put off some Daughter, who it may be lay upon his hands for want of a Portion. After a mighty Debate among our Country States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, it was resolv'd by a Vote of the Board, that no other Circumstance but this mention'd by my Neighbour could in any way extenuate the Bribery.</p>
            <p>I hapn'd to come in at the end of this wise De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, and found that skipping from one thing to another, the Company came at last to run down their Comrade, for imagining that 200 Guineas was a competent Portion for a Daughter of Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s. To bring off my Friend, tho at the expence of a piece of History, I was forc'd to tell them, That even in the time of the height of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire, such a Sum of Money would have been esteem'd a very considerable Portion for the Noblest and Greatest Senators of <hi>Rome</hi> to give with a Daughter: And that the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Immortal <hi>Scipio Affricanus</hi> (a Man not much inferior to Mr. <hi>G.</hi>) was said to have had a considerable Portion given her by the Senate (for her Father had nothing to give her, tho Master of the Spoils of <hi>Carthage</hi>) when it amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but to <hi>Two thousand pieces of Brass Money</hi>) which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95142:8"/>comes far short of <hi>Two hundred Guineas</hi> of ours.</p>
            <p>But to leaves this ridiculous Digression; if your Illustrious Body has done themselves Justice in their Vote against Mr. <hi>G.</hi> they had done much more so in those against <hi>the late Speaker:</hi> And no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can gain them greater Reputation abroad, than to hear of one in so high a Post, not only expell'd the <hi>Chair,</hi> but the <hi>House, for taking a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity after the passing an Act of Parliament.</hi> If it had been voted a <hi>Bribe,</hi> every body would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to have seen him expell'd; but to run up his punishment so high for a Gratuity only, and for a Gratuity given after the Act was past, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worthy of that <hi>nice Honour that has been ever so conspicuous in an</hi> English <hi>House of Commons.</hi> By this noble and just Procedure of yours, it will be made known to future Ages, that that which Custom may render allowable in other Men, and in other Stations, is yet <hi>a high Crime and Misdemeanor</hi> in any one that shall have the Honour to sit within <hi>these Walls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are told by the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> That none were admitted into the <hi>Great Council of the Jewish Nation,</hi> who had the least Stain upon his Reputation or Honour; nor were they allowed even to ask a just Debt of a Man <hi>while his Suit depended before them,</hi> lest it should be thought <hi>he paid it out of fear.</hi> As
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95142:9"/>the <hi>Room</hi> where they sat was open above, to put them in mind of that All-seeing Being that look'd down upon them from his <hi>Emperean</hi> Throne in so solemn an Occasion; so they were not so much as <hi>to touch Money</hi> upon any account whatsoever that Morning they met, and were <hi>to wash their Hands at the Door as they enter'd.</hi> And all this to intimate that <hi>Superlative Purity,</hi> which became the <hi>Members</hi> of so Sacred an Assembly.</p>
            <p>If you had voted your <hi>late Speaker's</hi> Fault to have been <hi>Bribery,</hi> and upon that had expell'd him, you had not done your selves so transcendant a piece of Justice, nor given Mankind so clear and illustrious an Idea of your <hi>untainted Probity,</hi> and that <hi>impartial Concern</hi> you have for the Country you represent. But in inflicting such a publick Mark of your Displeasure upon him for a Fault of a <hi>softer Name,</hi> you have rais'd to your selves lasting Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents in the Hearts and Affections of all Good men, and have <hi>left to Posterity the exact Standard of what sort of Man, a Member of the</hi> English <hi>Sanhedrim ought to be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when all is done, what a just Indignation must it raise in every one that loves his Country, to see it possible for <hi>Corruption</hi> so far to enter into that <hi>Chair,</hi> as to take Money for an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This is a monstrous Production in Nature,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95142:9"/>unknown to the Ages past, and only to be found in this. To take a <hi>Gratuity</hi> for an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ill enough, but to take one for an Act in favour of <hi>Poor Orphans,</hi> for an Act in which, not only the Honour of the Nation, but the Subsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of some hundreds of People of good Fashion and Quality, <hi>that wanted Bread and must have starv'd without it;</hi> to take a Gratuity for such an Act, is a thing scarce to be parallell'd. This was <hi>to Rob the Poor</hi> with a witness. A Crime which we see every day, the Wretches that Pad upon the <hi>High-way</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain to commit.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Poet</hi> had reason to exclaim against <hi>the Sacred Hunger of Gold</hi> in the times he liv'd in; but had he liv'd in ours, he had had much more reason to do so. There are some Men now a days that behave themselves in this Government, as if they thought themselves <hi>in an Enemies Country.</hi> Their manner of taking Money looks like <hi>the Sacking of a Conquer'd Town;</hi> for whatever comes in their way is with them <hi>fair Plunder.</hi> If a Stranger were to come in amongst us, and observe those People's Actions, he should take the Nation to be <hi>upon the point of breaking,</hi> and some Men for <hi>Bankrupts,</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to carry off what they can of the <hi>Publick-Stock.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:95142:10"/>
            <p>The Impostor <hi>Warbeck</hi> either was, or feign'd to be more tender of his Native Country, than these Gentlemen are. When with the Assistance of a Neighbouring King, he came into <hi>England</hi> to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate his pretended Right to the Crown, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press'd with Tears in his Eyes, the concern he had for the Havock his Army made in the <hi>Northern</hi> Counties, and wish'd he had rather never been born, than to be the occasion of so much Spoil, tho in a just Cause. If he was not sincere in his Grief, it was true Policy in him to appear so. And the wisest of Kings took a right way to find out the true Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Child, by putting her natural Affection upon the severest Trial.</p>
            <p>I would ask you a Question, Whether you think these Men that take Money with both hands from their own Country-men, might not be tempted to take the same from the Enemies of it? For my part, if I were to follow that <hi>Trade,</hi> I should ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deal with a <hi>French,</hi> than with an <hi>English</hi> Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomer: And it seems to me more generous in it self, and less hurtful to my Country, to ease the <hi>French</hi> Monarch of some of his superfluous Cash, than to rob my Neighbours here at home of any part of theirs.</p>
            <p>But perhaps you'll tell me, these Gentlemen are true to the <hi>present Government,</hi> and can never be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95142:10"/>tempted into another <hi>Interest.</hi> No thanks to them for the first, for they gain by it: And as to the second, I can scarce believe but its rather for want of being able to better their Condition, than for any Principle or hearty Affection to ours. For it is natural enough to conclude, That he who can be bought with Money, will yield himself to him that bids most.</p>
            <p>If these Men instead of <hi>pilfering</hi> at Home, could find a way to take Money from our Enemies, in the manner, and with the design, that it's said, a late Minister of <hi>France</hi> took that of a Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing State, I should heartily forgive them. The Story goes thus, Monsieur <hi>Colbert</hi> acquainted his Master with an offer had been made him of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Pension from a Foreign Minister, if he would ingage to give him notice from time to time, of the <hi>French</hi> Designs. The King not only allow'd, but commanded him to accept of it, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down at the same time a Scheme how the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence to be given, should keep up <hi>Colbert</hi>'s Credit with that Foreign Minister, but withal should be of Advantage to the <hi>French</hi> King. Thus <hi>the one had his Pension, and the other was egregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously cheated both out of his Money and Intelligence.</hi> A nice kind of <hi>Counter-plot,</hi> and to be intrusted with none but those, whose Fidelity a Prince has as much
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95142:11"/>reason to be assur'd of, as the <hi>French</hi> King of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>Colbert</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>But alas! my Friend, when once the love of Money gets the Ascendant, all other Passions and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests must stoop to its Sway: And Gold with a Man of that Temper-will prove too heavy, <hi>tho his Country and his Religion were laid together in the Scale.</hi> It was a severe Exclamation of <hi>Jugurtha,</hi> when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sold and betray'd to <hi>Scilla,</hi> he was brought within view of <hi>Rome. O! urbem venalem</hi> (says he) <hi>&amp; quandoque perituram si haberet emptorem. O Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary Town! that one time or another must needs perish, if ever it chance to meet with a Buyer.</hi> A saying that will be true to the end of the World of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions where <hi>Corruption</hi> and <hi>Bribery</hi> get once foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Your late <hi>Speaker</hi> was certainly a Gentleman, whose great Parts and Abilities, fitly qualified him for the <hi>Chair.</hi> If I had been worthy to sit in that House, I know not but from a mistaken Zeal for its Honour, I might have err'd upon the other side, and determin'd my Vote by a remarkable President in <hi>Roman</hi> History, which possibly I might be fool enough to apply to his Case. A Pro-consul of <hi>Asia,</hi> being accus'd before the Senate, for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king from the People of his Province a <hi>Present</hi> of fine Horses, rich Tapistry Hangings, and other
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95142:11"/>Houshold Furniture of great Value: His Plea was, That they were given him unask'd. His Accusers insisted upon the great Danger there was, of his being induc'd by these Gifts to pervert Justice in favour of the Givers. Upon a full hearing <hi>he was acquitted,</hi> and the reason which the <hi>Senate</hi> gave for it, was, <hi>That it was not to be so much as suppos'd, that a Present could possibly corrupt a Proconsul of</hi> Rome. But the World, you'll say, is mch chang'd since that time, and <hi>we are not</hi> Romans.</p>
            <p>But for all this, No People punish'd Bribery more severely than they did, of which I shall give you but one remarkable Instance. <hi>Julius Syllanus,</hi> the <hi>Praetor,</hi> was accus'd for <hi>Bribery,</hi> and the Senate appointed a day to hear the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint. His Father, the Famous <hi>Manlius</hi> begg'd of the Senate, that the Cause might be referr'd to him, which was granted. Upon hearing both Parties, <hi>he found his Son guilty, and condemn'd him to lose his Head.</hi> Not only so, but <hi>he refus'd to assist at his Funeral,</hi> and the day of his <hi>Execution,</hi> he gave Access at home to every body that had Busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness with him. So just a Horror, and so noble an Indignation had <hi>Manlius</hi> for his Son's Crime, that paternal Affection, the softest of Passions, took no place, where he thought the Honour and Justice of his Country was concern'd.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:95142:12"/>
            <p>It's a true Remark of the Duke of <hi>Rohans, That the Repute of Justice and Integrity does oftentimes contribute more to the Support of a State in difficult times, than either their Arms or Military Skill can.</hi> It was <hi>that</hi> which buoy'd up that little Government of <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> against all its Neighbours much more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful than themselves, during the Succession of some hundreds of Years. But when once they came to degenerate from their Ancient Virtue, all the <hi>Spartan</hi> Valour so much fam'd in History, was not able to save them from Ruin; tho as <hi>Thucidides</hi> observes, <hi>They were as good Soldiers then as at any time before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's in vain then for our King to have rais'd the Reputation of <hi>England</hi> in point of War to a greater height than it has been since the beginning of this <hi>Century;</hi> or to have acquir'd to <hi>Us</hi> a large Room in the Affairs and Counsels of our Neighbouring Kingdoms and States, which we either never had, or utterly lost. It's in vain for him to expose his Person in Battel for our Sakes, or for Us to have the Glory to see a King of <hi>England</hi> at the Head of a Mighty Army on the <hi>Continent,</hi> which has not happen'd in any of the Seven Reigns before him. In vain are we now Masters not only of the Ocean, but of a Sea we never pretended to: Or that by the Example and Conduct of a Warlike Prince,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95142:12"/>the <hi>English</hi> Courage has regain'd its Ancient Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation both at Sea and Land. It's in vain we are restor'd to our Laws and Liberties, or that we feel none of these Miseries that other Nations lie under. It's in vain (I say) all this, as long as <hi>Virtue, Probity,</hi> and <hi>Love to our Country</hi> are wanting, and we by our Corruption and like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious Practices, weaken the Foundations of our Happiness. The King will reap Immortal Praise for all his Toil: But of Us it shall be said by way of Reproach to after Ages, <hi>That such a Nation might have been Happy, but they would not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The World was once blest with an <hi>Epaminondas,</hi> that by his <hi>Military Virtue</hi> rais'd a People far short of <hi>Us</hi> in extent of Dominion or Riches, to a high pitch of Glory: But this Glory of theirs was of a short continuance. While that Illustrious Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral govern'd the <hi>Theban State, Thebes</hi> was both the envy and terror of <hi>Greece;</hi> Victory attended their Arms, and Success their Counsels. No sooner was he gone, but all their Laurels wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd, and they became a Prey to their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: Nor was he able with all his Virtue to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail Happiness upon a degenerated People any longer than his own Life. The <hi>Thebans</hi> were <hi>Thebans</hi> still, and the bright Example that <hi>Epami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nondas</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:95142:13"/>had set them, and the glorious Actions he had done, serv'd only to render their subsequent fall <hi>the more conspicuous, and the less pitied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Corruption comes once to over-run a Nation, Virtue its self becomes a Crime, and he that's guiltiest, is sure to fare best. It's a known Story to this purpose of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> writing to his Friend, a <hi>Vice-Roy</hi> of <hi>Mexico. You are here ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd</hi> (says he) <hi>of cheating the King of some Millions of Money in your Government. All I can say, is, if it be true, you are safe; if otherwise, you are undone.</hi> It was said of <hi>Cato, He was too good for the Age he liv'd in.</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> wisely foresaw the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that attends a Rigid Virtue in degenerated times: <hi>Be not over-righteous</hi> (says he); <hi>for why shouldst thou dye before thy time?</hi> In a vicious and corrupted Age, it were happy for a virtuous Man to be lost in the Croud. If he comes to be known, he runs the hazard of being undone. His Innocence is to other Men <hi>a tacit Reproach of their Crimes,</hi> and tho in spite of themselves they cannot restrain from paying in their thoughts a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Homage to his Virtue, yet at the same time they must needs hate him in their Hearts. <hi>A hard Fate,</hi> you'll say, <hi>for being good!</hi> But hard tho it be, let you and I endeavour to deserve it.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:95142:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Epicurus,</hi> you know, plac'd Happiness in <hi>that Pleasure and Delight which arises from a constant course of Vertuous Actions.</hi> All other Pleasures were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of that Excellent Man, whatever has been since said to the contrary by a <hi>Sect</hi> of Wretches that would shelter themselves under so Great a Name. It was the Pleasure of the Mind, the noble and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal part of Man, that the Philosopher meant: And he was much in the right on't. To grow Rich by <hi>Corruption,</hi> or to raise a Fortune by <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery,</hi> is but at best <hi>a Repentance dear bought:</hi> But to serve our Country from a <hi>publick and self-disin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terested Principle,</hi> carries with it a noble kind of Pleasure, and the only sort of Pride that's allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p>When Honour was the Reward of Good and Great Actions, It was more courted then, than Gold it self is now: And a <hi>Triumph</hi> or a <hi>Statue</hi> was infinitely more valu'd at <hi>Rome,</hi> than all the Riches of the East. Among our selves there has been found the like Spirit. At the time of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Invasion in 1588. most of the Noblemen and Gentlemen of <hi>England</hi> came chearfully in to serve Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and their Countrey, against the Common Enemy of both. A certain Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man came to the Camp of <hi>Tilbury</hi> with 300 men of his own Tenants and Retinue, and upon his own
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95142:14"/>Charge. Taking leave of his Wife at home, He bid her be chearful in his absence, <hi>For he hop'd at his return to make her a Lady;</hi> meaning he should be Knighted for his Good Service. All he aim'd at for the Reward of his Zeal and Expence for his Countrey, was the honour of Knighthood; <hi>a Mark of Favour in those days granted but to few.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have often regretted the hard fate of that great Restorer of Learning, the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon,</hi> who stands to all Ages an Illustrious Example of the Instability of Human Greatness, and withal an instance of the Justice of this Nation in the Case of <hi>Bribery.</hi> A great Man he was, and the Son of a great Father, and had attain'd to the highest Dignity in the <hi>State.</hi> All This Greatness, and all his Vast Accomplishments were not able to protect him from an Accusation of Bribery; and all that could be prov'd against him, was <hi>his allowing one of his Servans to accept a Present of a Suit of beaten Silver Buttons.</hi> For this single Fault, was he thrown down from his Preferments to the lowest Ebb of Fortune, and <hi>died in Obscurity for want of the Necessaries of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another great Man sunk under a like fate some Years after. <hi>Cranfield,</hi> Earl of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> Lord High-Treasurer of <hi>England</hi> was arraign'd for Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and Bribery. Neither the <hi>Treasurer's Staff,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:95142:14"/>nor the many eminent Services he had done the Crown could secure him from a severe Sentence. <hi>He was declar'd in Parliament incapable of Publick Trust, to lose his Vote in the House of Peers, to be committed to the</hi> Tower <hi>during Pleasure, and fin'd in</hi> 20000 l. <hi>For payment of which Fine, he was necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to sell a considerable Estate at</hi> Chelsea. If it were needful, I might run up to Ancient Times, and show how severely our Ancestors were pleased to punish this Ignoble Crime. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it's undeniable, that We and all other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have in all Ages of the World held it in the highest Detestation, I shall trouble you with no more.</p>
            <p>Perhaps you'll tell me, Those who gave your late <hi>Speaker</hi> the <hi>Gratuity</hi> mention'd in your <hi>Votes,</hi> were to blame. I think, No. If a man of that <hi>Sordid Principle</hi> will not do me Justice without Money, I know not why I may not give it him; rather than suffer by his Injustice. The Fault is none of mine: It's his, that would not do me reason without it. If one be unjustly pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess'd of a Thousand pounds of my Money, and I find that neither Honour, Conscience, nor Law, can prevail with him to restore it, I were want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my self if did not chuse rather to part with a hundred Pounds of it, than lose it all. He
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95142:15"/>is a Knave for keeping my Money from me, but I am not in the blame to treat him as I would do a Robber on the Highway, <hi>give him a part to save the rest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Canonists</hi> are nice enough in determining the particular Cares wherein it's blameable or lawful to give a <hi>Bribe</hi> or <hi>Gratuity,</hi> call it what you will. They all agree, That to give one in order to obtain an unjust thing, is a Crime both in the Giver and Receiver: But when one has to do with a Person that denies him a Matter, not only just in its self, but which by his Place he is obliged to grant, he that takes a Gratuity for doing it, is highly guilty; but he that gives it, is not only blameless, but has a right in Law to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Restitution of what he was necessitated to give.</p>
            <p>To come to the Case in hand. The <hi>Orphans Bill</hi> was one of the noblest and justest that ever was brought within these Walls. So many delays, it seems, were found out from time to time, by the late <hi>Speaker,</hi> That the Managers for the City of <hi>London</hi> saw it was impossible to carry it through, without giving a <hi>Gratuity</hi> to that Gentleman for it. They were neither to be Losers nor Gainers themselves, whatever way it went. They were only <hi>Trustees</hi> for the City, and for the Orphans,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95142:15"/>that must have perish'd if it did not pass. In or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to obtain then, an Act so Good and Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in its self, and so much both for the Honour of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and for the ease of poor Orphans, they chus'd rather to make the <hi>Present</hi> requir'd, than by not doing it, lose a general Good.</p>
            <p>I remember a Story that meets this Case. A <hi>Stoick Philosopher</hi> had solicited <hi>Dionysius</hi> the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of <hi>Sicily,</hi> often and long for Justice in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain business. He was delay'd from time to time. At last the Philosopher bethought himself of the only way to move the Tyrant to grant his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest. <hi>He comes to him one day, and prostrating himself upon his Face before him, kisses his Feet,</hi> as his other Court-Flatterers us'd to do. The Tyrant was so pleasingly surpriz'd with this unwonted Submis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the <hi>Stoick,</hi> that he immediately granted the Boon he had so often refus'd before. The rest of the Philosophers of that <hi>Sect</hi> were out of Humour with their Friend for so base a Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scention, and accus'd him of acting contrary to the Principles of their Philosophy. <hi>You have no reason</hi> (answer'd he) <hi>to be offended with my Carriage, when you consider the necessity of it. I hate the Tyrant and Tyranny as much as you do, but having a just Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest to ask of him, I made my Application for several
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95142:16"/>Years together in vain: Till finding that his Ears were in his Feet instead of his Head, I thought I could not be blam'd for applying to that part of him where he only could hear me.</hi> The Philosopher was certainly in the right. And since there are some men now-a-days that will not hear a just Request, except <hi>one speak to their Fists;</hi> It's no fault to apply to them in their own way, all others being ineffectual.</p>
            <p>But what a hopeful Condition is a Nation in when it comes to this! Where Money without Merit will open the Door, Fools and Knaves will be sure to enter sooner than Honest Men: And he that pays his Money, will certainly take care to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay himself where he can, tho at the expence of his Country. They have the same Plea for cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Publick, that a <hi>Counsellor of the Chattlet</hi> at <hi>Paris</hi> pleaded in <hi>Francis</hi> the First's time. He was accus'd for Extortion, and exacting more than his Fees. His Defence was, <hi>That truly he had bought his Place so very dear, That unless he took the Methods he was charg'd with, it was not possible for him to make up the Price he had given for it.</hi> However, It seems this Plea had no great weight with his Judges; For <hi>they Decreed his Money should be refunded to him, and he to pay it into the Hospital for the use of the Poor, and both the Buyer and Seller to be incapable of all publick Trust for the future.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:95142:16"/>
            <p>But when all is done, Sir, We have this to comfort our selves with, amidst all these dismal Reflections, That not only the Body of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion has a just abhorrence for <hi>those Corrupt Practices;</hi> but that in the <hi>Ministry,</hi> on <hi>the Bench,</hi> and in most <hi>Places of Trust,</hi> there are Men who by their Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple do all they can to bring Justice and Honour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to request. A <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> a <hi>Pembroke,</hi> a <hi>Sommers,</hi> or a <hi>Holt,</hi> are not to be found in every Age; and the less esteem we have for men that abuse their Places, the more we ought to have for those, who instead of inriching themselves at all hands on the Publick Cost, make it their aim to serve their King, and <hi>It,</hi> to the best advantage of both.</p>
            <p>Shall the <hi>French</hi> Subjects in spight of all the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Invasions made by that Monarch upon their Liberties, and of the innumerable Hardships and Miseries his Ambition has brought upon them, continue yet to serve him and their Country with an inviolable Fidelity: And at the same time shall We fall short, either in our Duty to a Prince that has restor'd Us to our Liberties, or in our Love to a Country, that we can much more properly call <hi>Ours,</hi> than the <hi>French</hi> have reason to call <hi>France</hi> Theirs, being their King is absolute Master of all? Let us imitate our Enemies in what's noble and just; and while our King does what's possible to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95142:17"/>raise us to (at least) an equal Level with them in point of War, Let us not fall short of them in those Vertues that are absolutely necessary to make a Peace when it comes, to be lasting and happy.</p>
            <p>I have done, when I have told you, That this Letter is writ with the same freedom which you have always allow'd me; And that I am, Intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Yours.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>